Okay then, welcome to our yoga class today. I just wanted to start off and just
by talking
a little bit about yoga philosophy before we go into the physical practice. I
also think
this is the perfect time to have a yoga call considering it's the one up to
Christmas and
I mean maybe not for you y'all over there, maybe it doesn't feel like Christmas
so much
doesn't really feel like F&P but in you know back home I'm sure people are very
stressed
with Christmas. Hey Kat. Hiya. Hello, how are you doing? Good sorry for the
delay, I'm
here. No don't worry we had a bit of an issue so we've only just started
actually so yeah
I'll carry on. So yeah I think it's nice to you know take a moment just to be
in the
moment and not be in such a rush and you know going for the destination. Okay
and before
we start as well I would like to say and obviously yeah it's nice to come along
today to this
practice and do it alongside me but it'll be also good to go to a class where
you can
have an instructor actually watch you in person and tweak your postures. I can
obviously see
you on this screen but I can't see you properly as I would in person so make
sure you've got
the postures right it basically is what I'm trying to say. Go to a yoga
instructor and
just yeah make sure you're doing them more correctly. Okay so yoga philosophy.
Yoga is
much more than just a physical practise it's a way of life. Yoga is similar to
Buddhism
but it originated in northern India 5,000 years ago. The main philosophy of
yoga is simple.
Mind, body and spirit are all one. The ultimate goal of yoga is a sustained
state of pure
awareness. Yoga is the transcendence of the mind to realise the true self or
the higher
self. This experience of pure consciousness is our true nature. Yoga has taught
me so
much like since I've started yoga it's taught me a lot. It's taught me to come
back to my
breath and back to my consciousness and everyday life not just when I'm
practising but you
know just when I'm just going about my normal life. It's taught me to love,
nourish and
care for my body. I've never felt stronger, healthier than I have now and yoga
is a big
part of why I feel that way. I feel a lot more present and calmer and in the
moment
and I feel more at peace and my body feels more open and freely moving. So yeah
and when
I don't practice for a little while I noticed that for sure that my body tight
ens up and
I'm also quicker at reacting you know to like negative situations whereas when
I'm practising
daily I'm more centered I feel okay so we'll talk a little bit about the breath
before
we go on to our physical practice because in yoga it's all about the breath and
even
in life it's all about the breath. So for example if you're feeling stressed or
anxious
or you know you're getting whipped up what do people tell you? Just breathe,
just breathe
because if we come to our breath and we keep our breath nice and elongated and
nice and
deep not short and fast and shallow we can really master our you know our life
and how
we react to situations and how we feel about situations. So one is all now to
start coming
back to our breath. So breathe gently and slowly try and slow down the breath
and breathe
deeper and elongate your exhalation but without any force or pressure and get
used to being
conscious about your breath and being aware of your breath. When we're
practising today
if you feel any pain don't resort to a shallow tense breath trying to breathe
through the
pain with a deep breath and on each exhalation just let it go let the pain go
let the stiffness
go let the tightness go. And finally yoga the physical practice of yoga has a
two prongs
effect and the main reason why we practice yoga is all about meditation. So the
first
the first prong is to be more flexible, more relaxed and more in our bodies and
this is
so we can sit comfortably in the cross legged or kneeling position while med
itating without
being interrupted by any pain or any discomfort so that's one of the first
reasons why we
practice yoga is so we can meditate basically with our pain and secondly while
you are actually
practising half a yoga it's a form of physical meditation as you are focusing
on the breath
and you are basically you know focusing on one thing you're creating a med
itative state
and this is pure meditation. So now it's time to get started with our physical
practice
what before we do we'll just take free long deep breaths and we'll do the free
free rule
or method which is basically three seconds in as you're breathing in, three
seconds hold
and then three seconds select the breath out and we'll do this three times. So
we'll begin
so let's breathe in, two, three, hold, one, two, three and exhale, one, two,
three. Something
I didn't mention in yoga when we're practising we will breathe in and out
through the nose
so we'll start this now. So once again in with three seconds
again and we'll do this one more time just in case the first time we didn't
breathe
through our nose. Okay I already feel a little bit calmer and a little bit you
know more relaxed
ready for the practice. So we're going to start our practice with a sun sal
utation this
is something that so a sun salutation is basically to salute the sun. It's a
continuous practice
of this and I will show you the pastures and we can do this you know one two
five ten times
in the mornings it's good to maybe do it ten times a day and you can always you
know add
more and more onto your practice but if you just start with this this is great
because
the sun salutation will bring more strength it will bring more flexibility and
tone to
the body it will open up your hamstrings shoulders chest and it will lease
tension as you're
moving through the poses you're lubricating your joints so it's basically a
really amazing
thing to do it's getting you ready for your practise it's getting you ready for
your day
and it literally takes five minutes to do five so if you've got five ten
minutes in the
morning you can do five or ten sun salutations okay so let's start I'm going to
head back
to my mat also put some yoga music on because why not
okay so I will talk you through the pastures first and the sun salutation and
then we'll
do all together can you just give me a thumbs up somebody just to make sure you
can hear
me right now yes okay perfect okay then so with the sun salutation we're going
to start
in a mountain pose and mountain pose is basically just a conscious or bright
standing pose so
when I say conscious I basically you know some people might stand a little bit
to the
side or I mean I'm sure I do this too I mean not some people all of us we all
just have
a set of hearts of our work that we add more weights onto that we we always
want to sorry
so with the mount pose we don't want to make sure our hips are in line with our
feet so you know
we're not standing like this or like this we're just standing nice and straight
nice and square
and with our posture as well we are afraid we're not hunched over not lean in
and we can
bring our hands to the side like this so if we are strong powerful stable not
me yeah music is a bit loud okay compared to your voice okay I've just lowered
the music down
thank you for that yeah that's true thank you thank you is it okay it's better
yes thank you yeah
okay thank you thank you for that thank you for letting me know okay so
mountain pose we got our
feet in line with our hips our hands out to the side our back nice and straight
you know so nice and our body's open already and we're just going to take a
deep breath
in mountain pose in through the nose and out through the nose
and on the next breath we're going to reach up and up with our hands above our
head
and do a slight back bend like this
and as we exhale we're going to bend over into a forward bend
when we bend over we want to bend from the hips from the hip joints
we don't want to bend we've got back we want to try and bend at the hips like
so
so we're not bending like this
but bending like this okay so we'll go through that again so start in mountain
pose
and we'll take a deep breath and as we breathe in we go up and as we exhale we
bend over
so we breathe in with the nose
and exhale
okay now that we're here we're going to take another breath in and out and as
we do we're
going to lift our head above our heart and as we breathe out we're going to
walk our feet back
I'll show you how it goes don't worry about getting it right this first time
because
we're going to go over this a few times
okay so breathe in
and exhale place our hands down and walk our feet back and when we're here we
're going to come down
and then we're going to plant our feet onto the floor like onto our toes sorry
and lift up as we inhale into upward facing dog
very stretch up a lower back
and on the next breath we're going to push back into downward dog
okay so when we're in downward dog you can move your feet back and forth like
this
to very stretch out your calves and just fall the back of your legs
you also want to be aware of your shoulders and your and your back you don't
want to be
hunched up you want to try and pull your shoulders away from your ears
and push push into the into the posture we're just staying this one for the
moment just to
open up the body remember to breathe deeply in and out through your nose nice
and slow and nice and deep
and on the next breath we'll start to walk our feet back to our hands
nice and slow be gentle with your body
especially on the face postures
okay now we're in a forward bend we're going to breathe in and out again
but lift our head above our heart and bend over again like so breathe in
and breathe out
and finally on our next breath we're going to stand up so breathe in
reach your arms above your head
and breathe out back to mountain pose
okay so that was the sun salutation and this is what I always mentioned in
before that we can
do um five ten of them every single morning just to activate your body and get
it ready for the day
or ready for your practice so we'll go over this a few more times I will show
you once now really
quickly and then we'll go through it together again just so you can see the
full and the full
sweet sequence okay I'll do it very fast
okay so we'll go through that together a few more times
so if you want to get to the front of our mat and get in mountain pose
okay we'll start in three two one breathe in and reach up and bend back
breathe out fold over
breathe in head above heart
breathe out place hands on the floor and walk your feet back
lower yourself down onto the feet breathe in
both face and dog
breathe out and sit down with dog
stay here for a moment just to let your body open up
keep the leg straight keep the back straight
shoulders away from the ears and push your chest into the floor
okay breathe in start to walk forward
and out
breathe in head above heart
and out bend over
and breathe in and come up
and out
okay
I'm gonna check the chart no I'm good okay okay so we'll go through that a
couple more times
okay we start in mountain pose
I'm actually going to show you a variation this time so instead of walking our
feet back and
forward we can actually jump them back and jump them forward you don't have to
do this
it's something you can wake up to or you can try it now but I'll show you our
variation now too
okay so mountain pose the front of our mat
stay nice deep breath in as we reach up and bend over and back sorry
and breathe out
breathe in
I know it's okay so when I jump back and lower down
I know it
and just play with the downward dog move your feet about push yourself in more
and just enjoy the opening let you feel throughout your body
okay so now I'm going to jump my feet in you can walk in or you can try jump it
in
so I'm going to bend a little bit and then I'm going to jump forward to the
front of my mat
okay so breathe in lift our heads up
and out
breathe in
okay we'll do this one more time and then we'll move on to some different post
ures
but as you can see it literally takes a minute to run through the sequence
so you can do it quite a lot of them in the mornings and they'll really just
set you up for
the day and even if you've only got five minutes you know I think we can all
spare five minutes
if you try to
okay so get in my own pose let's plant our feet
I'm going to awaken our feet as well I like to do this so I'm tapping the stars
on my practice
just coming back and forth on my feet and just get them ready for the practice
okay
breathe in and out
and in
breathe out
and breathe in
out
breathe in
and out
and breathe in
okay how did that feel does that feel okay
yeah okay great okay yeah nice nice and flexible yeah that felt good
nice yeah you know what honestly just doing them like I said even if you don't
do anything
else if you just do them doing them it really will change like how flexible
your body is and
yeah and you've got a lot stronger and yeah like had just said it's a warm up
you're basically
warming up and ready for the day or ready for your practice
okay so I thought that we would start off with some heart opening postures and
yeah I think it's nice to do these and you know because I think also it's nice
to do
heart opening you know just for what it is but then also a lot of us um maybe
work
on campus special not a lot of us we do we work on our laptops like sat on the
laptop all the time
maybe we're getting you know pain in our shoulders or on neck maybe we're hun
ched over on the third
maybe we're starting cars all day I don't know but yeah we just need to open up
and
um heart opening postures are a really great way to do this
if anyone would like to take a sip of water please go ahead
okay so we'll start with one of my favourite postures actually and um I'll
actually come a
little bit closer now okay so I don't actually know what this is called but I
'll show you this anyway
so we're gonna kneel on our mat even just kneeling like this I couldn't kneel
like this when I first
started practising yoga I couldn't kneel like this for about 30 seconds and
then I started to get
so much pain in my ankles and stuff like that so just do what feels good to you
and don't push your
body um but yeah maybe you'll be fine with this but yeah I didn't actually
realise how difficult this
was until I started to do this and I was like wow I can't even kneel on my own
knees but maybe I was
just very flexible so yeah just get into this type of position if you can and
then what we're going
to do is I'll show two different variations so this is a bit more of a um
beginner if you've not done
this posture before bring your hands behind your back and grab your elbows and
actively push your
chest out like this and you're going to really actively open up your back and
your you know your
shoulders your chest don't just go for the motion to just hold like this really
feel you know it all
open here that's the first variation and if you want to try something a little
bit more advanced
you can bring your hands into preposition behind your back like this
so we're going to do a preposition in our backs like so
it can it is quite difficult so don't worry if you can't do this straight away
I also couldn't
make some of these kind maybe some of these cards or do whatever's best for you
remember
we've got this one to start with okay so let's get into the position which ever
feels good for
each of you I'm going to take some deep breaths
this could be a moment to set an intention for the practice we would usually do
this at the very
start but I completely didn't mention that but we can do it now and that's fine
you might want to
set an intention of how you want the practice to go how you want your day to go
how you want
to feel after the practice you know if you want to send out any good energy to
people around you
or to yourself to feel into what you want from the practice today
remember to take deep breaths in through the nerves and out through the nerves
we'll do two more deep breaths remember to actively push open your chest
okay and on the next exhalation Josh Wallishians are behind your back
I've not done that one in a while I feel it in my wrists they're like oh that's
a bit
more stiff than usual okay so we're just going to go into child's pose now
child's pose is a really good pose to do and whenever you're in your practice
and it's maybe
going a little bit too fast or you need a bit of a breather and if you're
experiencing some back
pain child's pose it's a really nice pose to do and child's pose we're going to
bring off being
together yeah and so we're going to open our knees and we're going to set our
bone onto our
end of our heels we're going to bring our arms out of the bones of us we're not
going to walk
our arms forward until our chest is flat on the floor well try to bring your
chest flat on the floor
and your bed eye on the floor as well or on the mouth
and we're just going to sit here in child's pose think about and you know
actively
extend in your arms and open up your shoulders as well as your hips so yeah it
's a very nice overall
pose we're just going to sit in this for five breaths so just take five feet
breath on your own
and just come up out of the posture whenever you're ready
so
okay okay so the next posture is going to be poppy pose
so it's a little bit similar to the downward dog that we've just done the child
's pose that we've
just done sorry but instead of sitting our bone back onto our heels we're going
to keep our bone
up we're going to have our hands out in front of us and working forward again
so keep our bone in
the air and bring our chest to our mat and also our head so this is a very nice
opener for all
um here and for our heart so we've got like this and then do five breaths in
this posture
okay and come on whenever you're ready
and our final heart open and posture is going to be camel pose so once again we
're on our knees
with this time we're going to raise up forward like so we're going to have our
feet separated
or on a 90 degree angle all in line and we're going to reach back with both
arms and grab our
ankles so as we breathe in and breathe out
this might be a little bit difficult for some of you so we kind of um that was
the probably the
more advanced but I'll show you the beginner variation so the beginner
variation would just
be to put your hands behind your back like this and push forward like this
and let your head back don't go to hands too far just hold it hold it about
here
so get into whatever variation feels good to you stay in there for five breaths
and then
pretend back to a normal seated position
feel the stretch down the front of your legs your shoulders your chest
all your hips open
nice long deep breaths and breathe into the non-contability and allow its
release with each breath
okay great
okay so now we've done some heart open up postures we're going to finish with
some hip opening postures
okay so our first hip opening posture is one of my favourites and I always do
this
with people I I do it with you yellow a few times I always like to do this one
because
it always feels so good to me so I like to share that with others
okay so the first hip opening posture and it's good for the hips but then I'm
going to add a
variation which is really good for the neck as well which is one of the reasons
why I love this
posture I'm just going to get on our mat I'm going to stand up our legs quite
far apart so
favourite part then then the hips and we're just going to do a forward bend so
as we breathe in
we're going to bring the arms up and bend back slightly and as we breathe out
we're going to bend
forward okay
okay so for all in our mat ready let's breathe in
and out
try to reach your hands to the floor
let your head hang over and breathe position your feet if you need to feel too
actively push your hips back and your end the goal is to basically bring your
stomach
to your thighs or in between your thighs
you can hold the back to your ankles to pull yourself in
you can hold the floor wherever you feel let's take two deep breaths in this
posture
and then for the variation well just for the added extra we're going to bring
our hands
behind our backs like this interlace our fingers and then we're going to pull
our hands over our
head like so so let your head hang down between your legs bring your hands over
your head keeping
the arms straight and let's take two more deep breaths in this posture
whatever your ready release the hands return to centre
and the next breath slowly come on
bring arms up reach up
okay so I really like that one and another thing you can do in that one is when
we're over
we've also come over to each side I mean we won't do this now because you want
to get through
some more postures but we'll come over and stretch onto this side
stretch onto that side and oh yeah it's a really nice hip open up posture
okay when you would like to drink some water please do so
okay so the next posture we're going to go through is called goddess
so once again we're going to have our feet in favour of the other part in our
hips
we're going to turn our feet out to the side as much as possible
don't go too far and lose balance just do whatever feels good to you
and then we're going to bend down like so
so show you from the side so the goal is to have your knees completely straight
out to the side
obviously I'm not fully there yet as you can see but that would be perfect to
get it like that
but just you know keep everything open and straight try not to be hunched or
bent to either side
feel aware of your body in this posture okay
so you want this this is the part here that we're opening
do you actually want to push this forward
you can have your hands in position in front of you or you can bring your hands
out to the side
like this for the heart opener I will do this and we'll take five breaths in
this posture
[Music]
okay and come out whenever you're ready
nice okay what do we have next
okay the next posture is called pigeon pose this is a really really lovely pose
open up your hips when I was suffering with sciatica this was a nice pose to to
do to help
me get through that and it's crazy because I just thought that that was
something I used to have
all of the time I used to always get sciatica in my left glute since practising
I never ever ever
get it so yeah yoga is just great great all round okay so to get into our
pigeon pose
we're going to start it in a downward dog so we come to a downward dog
and what we're going to do is we're going to lift one leg so we'll start with
our left leg
we're going to lift it above and into the air and then bring it forward by our
hands
I'll show you first so you don't have to try and watch along
so you just know what to do so you're going to bring it up like this
we're going to actually stretch out like this for the moment and then we're
going to bring it
forward and bring it on in the angle in front and have our back leg straight I
'm going to sit like
this let me show you so my front leg is like this my back leg is straight so
this is the
portion we're going to be in okay so let's get back into downward dog if you
have his move
let's take a deep breath let's breathe in
and breathe out
and then next breathe in actually lift our left leg
and breathe our heart and then just allow your hip to open up
so you're here for the moment
okay and on your next breath bring your leg forward to buy your hands
nice and slow control
on top of your back and on top of your right toe your right toes so your foot
is flat on the floor
allow your front leg to be here and just get comfortable in the posture
you really feel this all around your hips and your legs
this is the page in pose we can also come forward and lie on our front in this
pose
or we can also push back in this pose I like to do I like to do all different
things in this pose
so let's take five deep breaths on this side
one thing to be aware of is make sure that your hips are in line with the floor
and there and your everything's parallel you're not you know over to the side
like this
and starting one bum cheek we want to just be completely and parallel to the
floor like this
so we're not like sat on the side or on this side
we are square on
okay let's do two more breaths
okay and on your next breath we're going to go into a posture
that's called half lord of the fishes which was a little bit strange when I go
down
see what it was called I was like huh so I'm going to do this I'm going to lean
over onto our left
and bring our right leg round be very careful and gentle because that was a
really um
you know strenuous posture on the body so you don't want to be doing any sort
of movements
bring your leg round all the way
and plant your foot on the floor next to your left leg and then we're going to
turn to the right
place our right hand back on the floor behind us and our left hand is going to
go here with our
elbow to our knee and we're going to look over our right shoulder
so it's complete spinal twist this is not a hip open posture this is more of a
spinal twist
but it's nice to add in after that posture as if it goes into it so nicely
so look over your left shoulder and take five breaths in this posture your
right shoulder sorry
this one is good to do if you're going to go to the toilet
just go to do this one as it will um so are your bowels and allow you to be
able to go to the toilet
okay one more deep breath and then we'll release ourselves out of the posture
okay slowly release come back release the hand release the leg
bring your leg round and then we're going to get back into downward jaw
slowly bring yourself back into all fours and then push back into downward dog
okay great now we're going to just repeat the curve sides on the other side
so let's take a deep breath in and lift our right leg
I'm going to stay here for a couple of breaths just to open up the hips
and on the next breath bring your foot forward your leg forwards and place it
by your hands
nice and controlled
on top of the toe on your left leg which holds even and sit into the posture
onto page and pose
whenever you've got your knee bent whenever you're doing any knee bent it's
good to flex your foot
as it will protect your knee
okay so we're going to take five breaths in this posture once again keep the
hips and
square and spiral out to the floor you can sit up or you can come down or you
can do a bit of both
okay two more five breaths
so
and if you're ready to we're going to head into the next posture so bring your
left leg round
then you know that you're right and bring your left leg round at front
bring your all the way around and place your foot onto the floor next to your
right leg
and this one as well you want to make sure both your palm cheeks are on the
floor
don't want to be over like this it might take you time to get to that but that
's fine
place your left hand on the floor behind you bring your right elbow to your
left knee
and look over your left shoulder
while keeping your right foot flexed to protect your knee
I'm going to stay here for five breaths again
actively push yourself around to the left going very nice by the twist
and keep the neck and the jaw and everything nice and relaxed if you feel any
tension in any of
the postures just come back to your breath and allow the tension to release
through each exhalation
remember to keep the jaw nice and relaxed as well this is an area that we tend
to tense open
hold our attention allow yourself to relax each out of your body
and on the next breath we can release ourselves from this posture
nice and slowly
I'm going to come back to downward dog to finish
hands on front of you
okay just come to a seated position on your mat
I'll see the position feels good to you while I see what we're going to do next
okay so we're going to finish with a posture called happy baby and then we're
going to go straight
into shavasana which is club's pose and this is something that we should do at
the end of our
practice just for a little bit of meditation at the end and also to thank
ourselves for our
practice breathe love into our body and yeah it's just a gentle way to end the
practice
so let's head to our mat and lie on our backs for child's pose and for happy
baby pose sorry
turn the line on our back we're going to grab our toes in the yoga grip so the
yoga grip is
two fingers together like this and we're going to hook our big toe and grab our
big toe if this is
too advanced for you and you're not at that flexibility yet you can grab your
knees or your
ankles or your shins I'm going to grab my toes so I'm just going to take my
fingers like this
place them into both my big toes and open my legs like this
so this posture is called happy baby because I'm sure we all see babies doing
this kind of thing
and you know doing all of this as they're rolling around so yeah I like this
one and I also like
to play with this one and open my legs you know do all of this with it
so yeah we'll take five breaths in this posture and you can stay like this or
you can play around
with it and you know open up your body
I'll show the em easier for your patients as well so you just needed a mix of
this as in
well feels with you.
And it's nice and clean happy babies are gently rock side to side as well.
Let's take two more breaths and then we're going to just line corpse pose which
I will show you next.
Okay so release your legs bring them out down to the floor and front of you.
Allow your feet to drop out to the sides and allow your hands and arms down to
the sides next year
with your palms facing upwards. So staying in this posture we'll like to talk
you through this.
So this is corpse pose or shavatana and we're going to use this as a relaxation
at the end of
our practice. So now we've completed our practice. You can relax here and close
your eyes
and I want you to take your breaths even deeper and even longer.
Thank yourself for showing up today and completing this practice.
Thank your body for allowing you to do this, allowing you to move through these
questions,
breathing and you know doing all of the beautiful things that it does all on a
zone give your body some love, some appreciation.
And also know that you are a little bit closer to being even more open and even
more free in your
body and remember to be patient with our bodies.
We never want to force any for any yoga. We never want to take to the point
where it's really
uncomfortable. Always want to be good in love and be nice and gentle with our
bodies.
And maybe we can come back to our intention as to why we started our practice
today.
It's nice to stay in shavatana for as long as you feel too but for today we
will end
our shavatana on the next breath. Usually we wouldn't rush through this but
when you practice
on your own you can stay in this for as long as you like. Sometimes you'll even
feel like
you've came out of your body and yeah that's a nice feeling and you have to
bring yourself back
to then get ready for the rest of the day. So whenever you're ready bring your
awareness
back to your body into the room that you're in. Start or wiggle around
and then turn over to either side and bring yourself up to the seated position
in your own time.
No rush.
Okay great.
And finally we will end our practice with a moment of meditation and a couple
of arms.
Okay so we'll sit on our minds in a cross laggard or seated position
and on kneeling position whatever feels good to you. We'll have our palms on
our knees.
We have our fingers like this if you like or you can just have your palms open.
This is actually to bring the energy into your body. This is why we have our
hands like this.
Let's bring the energy into you.
Okay so we're going to do three arms.
For each arm we're going to set an intention so for the first arm it's for our
self
so for the first one as you're arming think about get in love to yourself,
appreciation,
you know whatever you feel like you need in this moment give that to yourself
with the first arm.
With the second we're going to send that out. We're going to send all that love
and beautiful
energy out, out into all the animals, all the people, all you know the whole
if you know we're going to send that out into the if all that good energy to
every single being
and you know self in the if. And then for the third and final arm we're going
to send out the
energy even further to the universe to everything in the universe and it's all
going to come back
towards so like a big flow of energy. Okay let's get in position and take a
deep breath
you can close your eyes for this if you like.
And as we exhale we're going to arm so let's breathe in.
Okay then.
And breathe in.
Just take some deep breaths.
Have whenever you're ready come back to the bone, come back to your body and
your consciousness.
And with Namaste which is the light, women may,
knowledge is the light and the divinity within you. Namaste.